Guide to the Norvin Hein Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Norvin Hein Papers
1942-2018
RG 310
Yale University Divinity School Library
5
(12 boxes)
The collection provides an overview of Norvin Hein's long career as professor of comparative religion with a focus on Hinduism, serving on the Yale Divinity School and Religious Studies faculties for thirty-five years from 1950 until his retirement in 1985.
Hein, Norvin, 1914-2018
Arrangement
The collection is organized in seven series:
Series I. Correspondence
Series II. "Save the Quad" Documentation
Series III. Course-Related Records
Series IV. YDS/Yale Administrative Records
Series V. Writings
Series VI. Subject Files
Series VII. Audio-Visual Material
Biographical / Historical
Norvin Hein was born in 1914 in Ohio. He attended Wooster College, graduating in 1937. He was offered a teaching position in India following graduation, but since it would not begin for two years, he elected to attend Yale Divinity School. He interrupted his Bachelor of Divinity studies to take what was supposed to be a short-term position teaching English and religion in India, but World War II intervened. He ended up spending most of the war years in India, working for the Army YMCA and the crew of a U.S. Liberty Ship before serving as a chaplain's yeoman in a U.S. Maritime Service training station.
In 1945 Hein returned to Yale where he received his B.D. in 1946 and his Ph.D. in 1951. The religious practices that he had observed in India—religious street theater, especially—awakened him to an essential site-specific aspect of religion and forms of devotion that sprang from agrarian tradition. This became the focus of his dissertation and an eventual book, The Miracle Plays of Mathura (Yale, 1972).
Hein was appointed assistant professor at Yale in 1952, earning promotion to associate professor in 1958 and then full professor in 1975. From 1973 to 1976, Norvin was director of the S.T.M. program at YDS. He was Director of Graduate Studies in Yale's Department of Religious Studies from 1977 to 1985.
During the "Save the Quad" movement at Yale Divinity School in the late-1990s Hein played a crucial role in the successful effort to protect Sterling Divinity Quadrangle from demolition and keep YDS in its longtime home atop Prospect Hill. He did so by combing through legal documents pertaining to the bequest of John Sterling B.A. 1864, in which he discovered provisions that strengthened the Divinity School's case.
In addition to The Miracle Plays of Mathura, Hein authored and contributed to more than a dozen books and published more than two-dozen scholarly articles and reviews. Among his more enduring scholarly contributions was the 100-page section on Hinduism that he wrote for the well-known Religions of the World textbook (St. Martin's, 1983). Hein served as both Vice President and President of the American Society for the Study of Religion during the 1970s. He was a delegate and panelist at five different congresses of the International Association for the History of Religions.
Hein remained in the New Haven area following his retirement and continued his scholarly work, and his engagement at Yale and in the community. He died on April 29, 2018.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Norvin Hein family, 2018
Scope and Contents
This collection provides a glimpse into the professional life of Yale Divinity School graduate and Yale professor of comparative religion Norvin Hein (1914-2018). The documents selected for inclusion in the collection serve to highlight the major emphases of Hein's career - his extensive correspondence with students and colleagues, his involvement at Yale both in teaching and in the "Save the Quad" movement of the late 1990s, his writings and scholarly research, his administrative contributions to Yale, and his involvement in community activities such as the Cooperative Consumers of New Haven group.
The correspondence in Series I consists of letters between Hein and colleagues in his field both in America and abroad, students, and colleagues and administration at YDS.
For additional materials related to the "Save the Quad" documentation in Series II, see Record Group 53, Yale Divinity School Memorabilia Collection.
Course-Related materials in Series III include articles used in classes, book lists, bibliographies, lecture notes, and syllabi for courses taught by Hein. The materials pertaining to courses Hein himself took include his personal student notes.
For additional writings by Hein, see Record Group 27, Yale Divinity School Faculty Writings and Publications, Box 11. For additional "Save the Quad" documentation see Record Group 53, Yale Divinity School Memorabilia Collection.
Series VII contains rare film footage of the 1942 wedding of Indira Nehru to Feroze Gandhi, taken by Norvin Hein. An accompanying script describes the scenes in the film.
Educators; Hein, Norvin, 1914-2018; Yale University. Divinity School
- Correspondence, Series I
  - A (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - B (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Biswas-Byers (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Cain-Christian (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Chung-Culpepper (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - D (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - E (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - F (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - G (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - H (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - I (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - J (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - K (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Khopkar, Diwakar, 1967–1971 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Khopkar, Diwakar, 1972–1975 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Khopkar, Diwakar, 1976–1980 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Khopkar, Diwakar, 1982–1986 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Khopkar, Diwakar, 1987–1990 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Khopkar, Diwakar, 1991–1994 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - L (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - M (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - N (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - O (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - P-Q (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - R (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Sadler - Spurrier (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Staffner - Szeto (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - T - U (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - V (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - W (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Y, Z, Miscellaneous (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Save the Quad Documentation, Series II
  - Correspondence
    - Alumni, Letters from (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Barndt - Dittes (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Bryant, Robert (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Faculty, YDS (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Forman and Napier (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Hein, Jeanne (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Hiers, Richard (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - McCain - Preservation Miscellany (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Records of Correspondence - Society of Architectural Historians (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Sterling Building Maintainence Fund (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Stratford Historical Society - Wolterstorff (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Public addresses and clippings
    - Yale Alumni Magazine, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Save the Quad Campaign Update, 1997–1999 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Connecticut Preservation News, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - YDS Update, 1998–1999 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Yale News Releases, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Sterling Trustees, 2000–2001 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Questions Raised at Alumnal Meetings (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Notes
    - Unsent Letter to New Haven Register, 1996–2000 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Fact Sheets, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Annual Meeting for the Foundation for the Preservation of the Sterling Divinity Quad, 1997–1998 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Foundation for the Preservation of the Quad Finances; Receipts, 1997–1999 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Press Meeting Email, 1998–1999 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Dance of Divine Love, 1999–2005 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Subject files
    - Annual Fund (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Annual Fund Appeal and Crisis (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Claremont Group (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Divinity School Review Committee (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Feasibility Studies (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Future of Yale (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Gay/Lesbian/Straight/Bisexual Coalition Tension (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - President/Provost (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Yale Corporation (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Foundation for the Preservation of the Sterling Divinity Quadrangle
    - By-Laws, membership, background information, financial records (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - FPSDQ Trustee and Board meetings, 1997-2000 (Box 6, Folder 9-11, Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence and documents, 1995-2000 (Box 12, Folder 2-4)
- Course-Related Records, Series III
  - Courses taught
    - Comparative Religions - part 1 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Comparative Religions - part 2 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Departmental Courses (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Hindu Monotheisms; The Hindu View of Life (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Hinduism and Buddhism, 1954–1966 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Theistic Hinduism - part 1 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Theistic Hinduism - part 2 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Traditional Hinduism; Miscellaneous Courses (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Zen, Taoism, Shinto, Zoroastrianism and Islam; Varieties of Hindu Mysticism (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Courses taken by Hein
    - Religions of China (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - History of India (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Hinduism (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Psychology of Religion (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - 20th Century Literature of Religion (Box 8, Folder 5)
- Yale Divinity School / Yale University Administrative Records, Series IV
  - Publications (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - YDS Events (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Faculty meetings - part 1, 1978-1985 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Faculty meetings - part 2, 1978-1985 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Dean of Graduate School (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - YDS Committees, 1978-1984 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Budget planning, 1996 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Divinity School Review Committee - part 1, 1994-1995 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Divinity School Review Committee - part 2, 1994-1995 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Alumni materials (Box 9, Folder 7)
- Writings, Series V
  Scope and Contents
  For additional writings by Hein, see Record Group 27, Yale Divinity School Faculty Writings and Publications, Box 11.
  - Protestant Views of Hinduism, 1600-1825; Hardy's Disbelief, 1947, 1967 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Reviews of The Miracle Plays of Mathura, 1972, 1976 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Caitanya's Ecstasies and the Theology of the Name; The Rise of the Cult of Gopala, 1976, 1985 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - The Cult of Gopala; Kalayavana, A Key to Mathura's Cultural Self-Perception, 1986, 1989 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Rights to Miracle Plays of Mathura, 1989–2004 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Comments: Radha and Erotic Community; Protestant Views of Hinduism, 1616-1825, 1990, 2018 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - The Image of the Greek in Indian Literature;The Ramcaritmanas in Mathura, no date (Box 10, Folder 3)
- Subject Files, Series VI
  - Black Students (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Haberman, David (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Jihad (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Krisht Vidya (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Preservation Issues, General (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Cooperative Consumers of New Haven, 1954-1960 (Box 11, Folder 1-4)
  - Spiritual Unity and Social Equality (Box 11, Folder 5)
- Audio-Visual Material, Series VII
  - Film of wedding of Indira Gandhi, 1942 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    50 ft. 10 mm. Kodachrome motion picture film shot by Hein.
  - "The Wedding of Indira Nehru - A Film Script" by Norvin Hein (2007, revised edition 2009) (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence and background information related to film, 2001-2018, 2000-2018 (Box 12, Folder 8)